Where did you go this time, Riptoes?
They're cutting right
through that mountain.
Look at the size of
those digging machines.
Long ago, ships sailed all the way around
South America to travel between the
Atlantic and Pacific Oceans.
The extra 8,000-mile
trip took many months.
Panama is a narrow strip of
land between the two oceans.
A canal is a human-made waterway.
Digging a canal there in Panama
would create a fast shortcut.
But building it would be
dangerous and difficult.
They almost didn't even
start because of the bugs.
Mosquitoes spread deadly
diseases to the workers.
Finally, an American doctor named William
Gorgas found a way to stop the mosquitoes
so building could safely begin.
Thousands of workers dug
through the thick jungle.
But a huge mountain blocked the path.
Ships could not sail themselves over it.
But removing the entire
mountain would be too difficult.
So engineers designed a system
of chambers called locks.
They created steps made of water to safely
lift the ships up and over the mountain.
Here's how they work.
A ship sails into a lock and
the gate closes behind it.
Water then fills up or drains out.
The water physically lifts or lowers the
ship until it can enter the next chamber.
This repeats until the
ship is all the way across.
Building the Panama Canal was a huge job.
What kinds of problems do you think
the engineers had to figure out?
They had to make giant doors strong
enough to hold all the water.
And figure out how to get the water
in the locks to lift the ships.
Engineers had to invent brand new ways to
control water so they could lift ships up
one side of the mountain and
lower them down the other.
Because of the canal, a trip
that used to take many months now
takes less than one day.
The Panama Canal opened in 1914.
Today,
thousands of ships use it every year to
share food and goods around the world.
What an amazing invention!
The water does all the lifting.
And it almost didn't happen
because of a bunch of mosquitoes.
I'm glad they figured it out.
Now it only takes a day to
get across instead of months.
If you could build a shortcut to
anywhere, where would you want to go?